First Report
Volume One
Death Disguised
THE
<PERSON>SHIPMAN</PERSON> INQUIRY
Chairman: <PERSON>Dame Janet Smith</PERSON> DBE
First Report
Volume One
Death Disguised
July 2002
THE
<PERSON>SHIPMAN</PERSON> INQUIRY
Chairman: <PERSON>Dame Janet Smith</PERSON> DBE
‘None of your victims realised that yours was not a
healing touch. None of them knew that in truth you
had brought her death, death which was disguised
as the caring attention of a good doctor.’
The Honourable Mr Justice <PERSON>Forbes</PERSON> when sentencing
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> on 31st January 2000
© Crown Copyright 2002
The text in this document may be reproduced free of charge in any
format or media without requiring specific permission. This is subject
to the material not being used in a derogatory manner or in a
misleading context. The source of the material must be acknowledged
as Crown copyright and the title of the document must be included
when being reproduced as part of another publication or service.
Any enquiries relating to the copyright in this document should be
addressed to HMSO, The Copyright Unit, <ORGANIZATION>St. Clements House</ORGANIZATION>,
2-16 Colegate, <LOCATION>Norwich</LOCATION> NR3 1BQ. Fax: 01603 723000 or
e-mail: copyright@hmso.gov.uk
1
Foreword
The Inquiry’s Terms of Reference required me to consider the extent of <PERSON>Harold Fredrick
Shipman</PERSON>’s unlawful activities but left it to me to decide how this should be done. Within a very
short time, I came to realise that the only way in which to satisfy the reasonable expectations of
the families and friends of <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s former patients was to provide, so far as I could, a
decision in each individual case in which suspicion might arise. The work of investigation and
decision writing proved to be far greater than I had anticipated and has taken longer than I had
hoped. I believe that this First Report provides as complete and accurate an account of
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s criminality as it will ever be possible to give.
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> breached the trust of his patients and of the communities in which he lived. He has
caused unimaginable grief and distress. No one who reads this Report can fail to be deeply
shocked. I would like to express my profound sympathy to those who have been bereaved by
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s actions and also to those whose trust has been so callously betrayed.
I wish to thank the many witnesses who have enabled the Inquiry to carry out its task. I know
that, for some, the experience of providing evidence, whether orally or in writing, has been a
painful one.
Although the investigation of <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s crimes has at times been harrowing, there is one
particular respect in which it has been positively heart-warming. I want to express my
admiration and respect for the way in which the people of <PERSON>Hyde</PERSON> and <PERSON>Todmorden</PERSON> care so
affectionately for their relatives and neighbours. I have heard and read of countless families
where a son or daughter, son-in-law or daughter-in-law, niece, nephew or grandchild cared
devotedly for an elderly relation, sometimes visiting several times a day, while looking after his
or her own family and children and often coping with a job. I have heard many accounts of
kindness by neighbours.
The completion of this First Report is an important landmark in the life of the Inquiry. It provides
me with the opportunity to thank the Inquiry staff, who have worked unremittingly hard during
the last 18 months. I am grateful to the administrative team, led by <PERSON>Andrew Griffiths</PERSON> and
strongly supported by <PERSON>Oonagh McIntosh</PERSON> and <PERSON>Helen Owen</PERSON>. I express my admiration for, and
gratitude to, <PERSON>Henry Palin</PERSON>, who, together with <PERSON>Ita Langan</PERSON>, recruited and managed a team of
solicitors and paralegals. I thank the IT experts, in particular <PERSON>Michael Taylor</PERSON>, who have enabled
us to cope with an enormous quantity of information without drowning in a sea of paper. I am
grateful to Dr <PERSON>Aneez Esmail</PERSON>, the Inquiry’s Medical Advisor, whose help with medical issues has
been invaluable. Finally, I must mention the enormous assistance I have received from <PERSON>Caroline
Swift</PERSON> QC, <PERSON>Christopher Melton</PERSON> QC, <PERSON>Anthony Mazzag</PERSON> and <PERSON>Michael Jones</PERSON>, without whose
indefatigable industry and considerable talents my task would have been impossible.
<PERSON>Janet Smith</PERSON>
July 2002
2
The Shipman Inquiry
i
CONTENTS
SUMMARY
CHAPTER ONE Before the Inquiry
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s Professional Career: Training 7
The Move to <ORGANIZATION>Todmorden</ORGANIZATION> 7
<ORGANIZATION>Shipman</ORGANIZATION>’s Abuse of Pethidine 7
Discovery 9
Criminal Proceedings 9
A New Job 10
Possible Disciplinary Proceedings 10
The Move to <ORGANIZATION>Donneybrook</ORGANIZATION> 11
The Market Street Surgery 12
The Police Investigation of March 1998 13
The Death of Mrs <PERSON>Kathleen Grundy</PERSON> 13
Investigating <PERSON>Mrs Grundy</PERSON>’s Death 14
Widening the Investigation 15
Suspension from Practice 15
The Criminal Trial 16
The End of <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s Professional Career 16
The Inquests 16
Further Police Investigations 17
The Laming Inquiry 17
CHAPTER TWO The Inquiry
The Setting Up of the Inquiry 21
<ORGANIZATION>Terms of Reference 21
Independence 21
Starting Work</ORGANIZATION> 21
Deciding How to Proceed 22
The First Report 23
The Application of the Coroners Act 1988 23
Identifying the Deaths to be <ORGANIZATION>Investigated</ORGANIZATION> 24
The Deaths Investigated 26
CHAPTER THREE The Evidence and the Oral Hearings
The Collection of the Evidence 29
The Arrangements for the Distribution of Evidence 31
The Opening Meeting 32
Representation 32
The Application to Broadcast 32
The Oral Hearings 33
The Oral Evidence 35
The Expert Evidence 35
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s Position 36
The Position of <PERSON>Mrs Shipman</PERSON> 36
Submissions 37
ii
The Shipman Inquiry
CHAPTER FOUR <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s <ORGANIZATION>Practice
Todmorden</ORGANIZATION> 39
<ORGANIZATION>Donneybrook</ORGANIZATION> 40
Market Street 43
Residential and Nursing Homes 47
CHAPTER FIVE The Existing Procedures for Death Registration and
Cremation Certification
Death Registration 49
Cremation Certification 55
The Future 61
CHAPTER SIX The Medical Evidence
Cardiac Causes of Death 63
Cerebrovascular Accident 67
Respiratory Conditions Causing Death 71
Cancer 74
The Presence of a General Practitioner at or shortly before a Patient’s
Death 74
The Deceased’s Position in Death 76
The Collapsed Patient 79
The Diagnosis of Death 81
The Effect of Heat 82
Estimating the <ORGANIZATION>Time of Death</ORGANIZATION> 83
The Patient who Refuses to Heed Medical Advice 84
CHAPTER SEVEN Drugs
Morphine and Diamorphine 87
<ORGANIZATION>Pethidine</ORGANIZATION> 96
<ORGANIZATION>Chlorpromazine</ORGANIZATION> 96
Other Types of Treatment by Injection 97
CHAPTER EIGHT <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s <ORGANIZATION>Acquisition of Controlled Drugs
Todmorden</ORGANIZATION> 99
Pre-Todmorden 102
Hyde 103
The Market Street Years 105
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s Time at <ORGANIZATION>Donneybrook</ORGANIZATION> 107
The Future 107
iii
CHAPTER NINE The Decision-Making Process
The Evidence in Individual Cases 109
Similar Fact Evidence 109
The Fifteen Convictions 110
The Significance of the Features Emerging from the Conviction
Cases 111
Standard of Proof 119
Findings of Unlawful Killing 120
Decisions that the Death was Natural 120
Cases where no Decision has been Possible 120
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s Terminally Ill Victims 121
Re-registration of Deaths 122
Allegations of Theft 122
Professor <PERSON>Richard Baker</PERSON>’s Review 123
CHAPTER TEN <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s Unlawful Activities: The Early Years
Pontefract General Infirmary 125
Locum Work 125
General Practice in <LOCATION>Todmorden 126
County Durham</LOCATION> 131
CHAPTER ELEVEN <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s Unlawful Activities: The Donneybrook
Years
The Period from 1977 to 1983 134
The Period from 1984 to 1989 139
The Years 1990 and 1991 157
CHAPTER TWELVE <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s Unlawful Activities: The Market Street Years
The Year 1992 159
The Year 1993 160
The Year 1994 164
The Year 1995 166
The Year 1996 168
The Year 1997 172
The Year 1998 174
CHAPTER THIRTEEN <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s Character and Motivation
Introduction 177
Motive 179
Other Explanations 181
Professional Reputation 181
Personal Relationships 183
Aggression, Conceit and Contempt 184
Dishonesty 186
Addiction 187
What Does This Constellation of Traits Reveal? 187
The Selection of Patients 189
The Interludes When <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> Did Not Kill 191
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s Downfall 193
After <PERSON>Mrs Grundy</PERSON>’s death 195
iv
The Shipman Inquiry
CHAPTER FOURTEEN Conclusions
The Numbers 197
The Typical Shipman Killing 197
The Report of Professor <PERSON>Richard Baker</PERSON>: Compatibility of Results 198
Deaths in Nursing and Residential Homes 199
Systems Failures and Tasks for Phase Two 200
The Betrayal of Trust 201
APPENDIX A ‘ The Relationship between the Findings of the Review
of <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s Clinical Practice and the Inquiry’s
Determinations’ by Professor <PERSON>Richard Baker</PERSON>, OBE
APPENDIX B Participants in Phase One of the Inquiry and their
Representatives
APPENDIX C Specimen Medical Certificate of Cause of Death (MCCD)
APPENDIX D Specimen Cremation Forms A, B, C and F
APPENDIX E Summaries of Conviction Cases
APPENDIX F Chronological List of Decided Cases
APPENDIX G Alphabetical Index of Inquiry Decisions
1
SUMMARY
1. <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> entered general practice in early 1974, when he joined the <ORGANIZATION>Abraham Ormerod
Medical Practice</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Todmorden</LOCATION>. He remained there until September 1975, when his
partners discovered that he had been dishonestly obtaining controlled drugs for his
own use.
2. In February 1976, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> pleaded guilty at the <ORGANIZATION>Halifax Magistrates’ Court</ORGANIZATION> to three
offences of obtaining pethidine by deception, three offences of unlawful possession of
pethidine and two further offences of forging a prescription. He asked for 74 similar
offences to be taken into consideration. He was ordered to pay a fine and
compensation.
3. The fact of his convictions was reported to the <ORGANIZATION>General Medical Council</ORGANIZATION>, which decided
to take no disciplinary action against him. The <ORGANIZATION>Home Office</ORGANIZATION> imposed no prohibition on
his future dealings with controlled drugs. He was, therefore, free to continue practising
as a doctor without limitation or supervision.
4. In October 1977, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> joined the seven doctor <ORGANIZATION>Donneybrook</ORGANIZATION> practice in <LOCATION>Hyde</LOCATION>. He
remained there until January 1992, when he began to practice single-handed from
within the same building.
5. In August 1992, he moved to new surgery premises at 21 <LOCATION>Market Street</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Hyde</PERSON>, where he
continued to work as a single-handed practitioner until his arrest in September 1998.
6. Throughout his career as a general practitioner, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> enjoyed a high level of
respect within the communities in which he worked. In <PERSON>Hyde</PERSON>, he was extremely popular
with his patients, particularly his elderly patients, and was regarded by many as ‘ the
best doctor in <PERSON>Hyde</PERSON>’.
7. In July 1998, the <LOCATION>Greater Manchester</LOCATION> Police began an investigation into the death of one
of <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s patients, <PERSON>Mrs Kathleen Grundy</PERSON>. That investigation was rapidly widened to
include the deaths of many other patients of <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>.
8. On 7th September 1998, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was arrested, interviewed and charged with the
murder of <PERSON>Mrs Grundy</PERSON> and with other offences associated with the forgery of her will,
under which he was to be the sole beneficiary of her estate. He was subsequently
suspended from practice and charged with 14 further murders.
9. On 31st January 2000, following a lengthy trial, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was convicted of 15 counts of
murder and one of forging <PERSON>Mrs Grundy</PERSON>’s will. He was sentenced to 15 terms of life
imprisonment and, for the forgery, a concurrent term of four years’ imprisonment. The
trial judge said that his recommendation to the Home Secretary would be that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>
should spend the remainder of his days in prison. Following the criminal trial, the
Director of Public Prosecutions announced that no further criminal proceedings would
be instituted against <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>.
10. Subsequently, the <ORGANIZATION>Professional Conduct Committee</ORGANIZATION> of the <ORGANIZATION>General Medical Council</ORGANIZATION>
erased <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s name from the medical register. 
2
The Shipman Inquiry
11. Before the trial and subsequently, the police investigated a large number of deaths of
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s patients where there was evidence that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> had been responsible for
the death. Those deaths were reported to the South Manchester Coroner, Mr <PERSON>John
Pollard</PERSON>. Between August 2000 and April 2001, he conducted inquests into 27 deaths of
patients of <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>, recording verdicts of unlawful killing in 25 cases and open verdicts
in the remaining two. On 18th May 2001, the Coroner opened inquests into a further 232
deaths; those inquests were immediately adjourned on the direction of the Lord
Chancellor, pending publication of the findings of this Inquiry.
12. On 31st January 2001, following resolutions of both Houses of <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION>, the Secretary
of <ORGANIZATION>State for Health</ORGANIZATION> issued the instrument of appointment establishing The <ORGANIZATION>Shipman
Inquiry</ORGANIZATION>, giving it the powers conferred by the Tribunals of Inquiry (Evidence) Act 1921
and appointing me as Chairman of the Inquiry.
13. The first of the Inquiry’s Terms of Reference requires it, ‘ after receiving the existing
evidence and hearing such further evidence as necessary, to consider the extent of…
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s unlawful activities’. In this, the Inquiry’s First Report, I set out my findings as
to how many of his patients <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> killed, the means employed and the period over
which the killings took place.
14. Volumes Two to Six of this Report contain my written decisions in 494 cases – 493
deaths and one incident involving a living person. Those decisions are based on an
enormous volume of evidence, which has been gathered by the Inquiry team.
15. I have found that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> killed 215 of his patients. The first, Mrs <PERSON>Eva Lyons</PERSON>, was killed
in March 1975, when <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was practising in <LOCATION>Todmorden</LOCATION>, and the last, <PERSON>Mrs Kathleen
Grundy</PERSON>, died in June 1998.
16. <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s usual method of killing was by the administration of a lethal dose of an
opiate, most frequently diamorphine. There is some evidence that he may have killed a
few patients by the administration of large doses of a sedative. There is no reliable
evidence that he killed by any means other than the administration of a drug.
17. Of the 215 killings, one took place in <LOCATION>Todmorden</LOCATION>, 71 during <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s time at the
<ORGANIZATION>Donneybrook</ORGANIZATION> practice and the remaining 143 during his six years at the Market Street
Surgery. While at the Market Street Surgery, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> killed one patient in 1992,
16 patients in 1993 and 11 in 1994. In each of the years 1995 and 1996, he killed
30 patients, increasing to 37 in 1997. During the first three months of 1998, he killed
15 patients, after which there was an interval of about seven weeks; he went on to kill a
further three patients before his arrest in September 1998.
18. <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s oldest victim, Miss <PERSON>Ann Cooper</PERSON>, was 93 years old when she was killed. The
majority of <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s victims were elderly but he did, on occasions, kill younger people.
Mr <PERSON>Peter Lewis</PERSON> died at the age of only 41; he was the youngest of <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s patients to
die at his hands. Mr <PERSON>Lewis</PERSON> was in the advanced stage of a terminal illness and <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>
hastened his death. The youngest of <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s victims to suffer an unexpected death
was Mr <PERSON>David Harrison</PERSON>, who was 47 years old when he died.
3
19. Of <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s 215 victims, 171 were women and 44 were men. In general, women live
longer than men, so that there are more elderly women than elderly men living alone.
Since <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s typical victim was an elderly person living alone, he found most of his
potential victims among his female patients. However, he also killed men when the
opportunity presented itself.
20. Whilst the majority of the deaths for which <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was responsible occurred while he
was working as a single-handed practitioner, it is nevertheless clear that, even
while working in a multi-handed practice, he was able to kill undetected over a period
of many years.
21. I have found that 210 of the deaths investigated by the Inquiry team occurred as the
result of natural causes and not by reason of any action on the part of <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>. I hope
that the families concerned with these cases will be reassured by my finding that
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was not responsible for their relative’s death.
22. There are 45 deaths for which I have found that a real suspicion arises that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>
may have been responsible, although the evidence is not sufficiently clear for me to
reach a positive conclusion that he was. In addition, there are a further 38 deaths in
respect of which there was so little evidence, or evidence of such poor quality, that I was
unable to form any view at all. These are mainly deaths dating from the early years,
where little documentary or witness evidence survives. I regret that the families
concerned with these deaths are left in a state of uncertainty, but it was inevitable that
there would be some cases where the evidence would not permit me to reach a positive
conclusion one way or the other. I can only hope that it will be of some comfort to the
relatives at least to know that the circumstances of each death have been investigated
as fully as possible.
23. In all, the Inquiry has examined 888 cases; I have given a written decision in 494
(493 deaths and one incident involving a living person) of those cases. In the remaining
394 cases, there was compelling evidence that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was not responsible for the
death. The Inquiry legal team therefore closed the files in those cases, without the
necessity for a written decision. In all but the most straightforward cases, I examined the
file and confirmed the decision to close it.
24. Professor <PERSON>Richard Baker OBE</PERSON>, Professor of Quality in Health Care at the <ORGANIZATION>University of
Leicester</ORGANIZATION>, conducted a review of <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s clinical practice, which was published in
January 2001. He carried out a number of analyses of the estimated excess of deaths
among <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s patients during his career as a general practitioner. He estimated that
the true number of excess deaths lay between 198 and 277 and concluded that an
excess of 236 deaths was ‘ most likely to reflect the true number of deaths about which
there should be concern’.
25. Having considered my findings, Professor <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> has concluded that they support the
conclusion that the excess of deaths is in the region of 220 to 240, i.e. very close to his
own figure of 236. Here, Professor <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> is taking into account, not only the 215 deaths
which I have found that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> caused, but also some of the deaths about which I was
unable to reach a positive conclusion but where I found that there was a real suspicion
4
The <ORGANIZATION>Shipman Inquiry</ORGANIZATION>
that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was responsible. It is inevitable that that group of deaths will, in fact,
contain some killings. The striking compatibility between the results of Professor <PERSON>Baker</PERSON>’s
previous review and my own findings strongly suggests that the conclusions of the
Inquiry and of the review are very likely to be correct.
26. All but three of the deaths for which I have found that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was responsible were
entered in the register of deaths in reliance upon Medical Certificates of Cause of Death
completed by <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>. The majority of those deaths were followed by cremation.
Before a cremation can be authorised, a second doctor must confirm the cause of death
and the cremation documentation must be checked by a third doctor employed at the
crematorium. These procedures are intended to provide a safeguard for the public
against concealment of the fact that a person has been unlawfully killed. Yet, even with
those procedures in place, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was able to kill 215 people without detection. It is
clear therefore that, in reality, the procedures provided no safeguard at all. Why that
was, and what steps should be taken to devise a system which will afford the public a
proper degree of protection in the future, are issues which the Inquiry will consider
during Phase Two.
27. <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s patients frequently died suddenly at home, without any previous history of
terminal or life-threatening illness. Such deaths should be reported to the coroner. Yet
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> managed to avoid a referral to the coroner in all but a very few cases in which
he had killed. He did this by claiming to be able to diagnose – and, therefore, to certify –
the cause of death and by persuading relatives that there was no need for a postmortem
examination. In Phase Two, the Inquiry will consider measures which can be
taken to ensure that all unexpected or unexplained deaths are reported and their cause
properly investigated.
28. After <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s convictions for drugs offences in 1976, he declared his intention never
to carry controlled drugs again. Accordingly, he was not obliged to have a controlled
drugs register. Yet he was able, by a number of different methods, to obtain large
quantities of controlled drugs; in 1996, he prescribed and obtained in the name of a
dying patient as much as 12,000mg diamorphine on a single occasion. That alone
would have been sufficient to kill about 360 people. Despite the fact that the possession
and supply of such drugs is said to be ‘ controlled’, those controls did not prevent
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> from acquiring large amounts of diamorphine without detection. How that
could happen, and what measures should be taken to strengthen the system of
controlling access to such drugs, are matters which will also be considered by the
Inquiry in Phase Two.
29. Professor <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> has observed that one implication of the high number of patients killed
by <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> is that an effective system of monitoring the death rates of patients of
general practitioners would have detected the excess number of deaths. No such
system was in place during <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s time in general practice. In Phase Two, the
Inquiry will seek to identify effective systems for monitoring death rates, and will
consider other possible improvements to the arrangements for monitoring general
practitioners and ways of encouraging those genuinely concerned about possible
5
misconduct on the part of doctors to express their concerns to those in a position
properly to investigate and evaluate them.
30. No one reading this Report can fail to be shocked by the enormity of the crimes
committed by <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> and to feel, as I do, the deepest sympathy for his victims and
their families. His activities have brought tragedy upon them and also upon the
communities in which he practised and which gave him their trust.
31. In its first Phase, the Inquiry has determined the extent of <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s criminality. We shall
now direct our efforts to attempting to devise improved systems so as to ensure that
such a terrible betrayal of trust by a family doctor can never happen again.
6
The Shipman Inquiry
7
CHAPTER ONE
Before the Inquiry
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s Professional Career: Training
1.1 In September 1965, <PERSON>Harold Fredrick</PERSON>*
 <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> entered the <ORGANIZATION>University of Leeds School of
Medicine</ORGANIZATION> at the age of 19 years. He spent five years there, training for his future medical
career. During that time, he married and the couple’s first child was born. <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> left
<ORGANIZATION>Leeds</ORGANIZATION> in 1970, having gained the qualification MB ChB.
1.2 From <LOCATION>Leeds</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> moved to <LOCATION>Pontefract</LOCATION>, where he was employed for 12 months as a
pre-registration house officer at the <LOCATION>Pontefract General Infirmary</LOCATION>, before being fully
registered with the <ORGANIZATION>General Medical Council</ORGANIZATION> (GMC) in August 1971. Thereafter,
he continued to work at the same hospital as a senior house officer, gaining a
diploma in child health (DCH) in 1972 and a diploma in obstetrics and gynaecology
(DRCOG) in 1974.
The Move to <LOCATION>Todmorden</LOCATION>
1.3 In the early part of 1974, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> answered an advertisement in a medical publication
and, after an interview, secured a position in a busy general practice operating from the
<LOCATION>Abraham Ormerod Medical Centre</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Todmorden</LOCATION>, a town in the <LOCATION>Pennines</LOCATION> on the
Lancashire/Yorkshire border. After a short probationary period as an assistant general
practitioner, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> became a junior partner in the practice, with a view to becoming
an equal partner in due course.
1.4 <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> impressed his partners with his competence, enthusiasm and capacity for
hard work. He was popular with patients. He persuaded his partners to adopt a more
modern system of categorising data contained in patient records and himself undertook
much of the work required to change to the new system. Another task that he undertook
was the disposal of a quantity of out-of-date controlled drugs which were stored in
the surgery’s controlled drugs cabinet. It also seems that he assumed responsibility for
re-stocking the cabinet and, on occasion, for ordering stocks of controlled drugs for use
by members of the practice.
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s Abuse of Pethidine
1.5 By February 1975, the <ORGANIZATION>Home Office Drugs Inspectorate</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>West Yorkshire Police
Drugs Squad</ORGANIZATION> had become aware that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was obtaining abnormally large
quantities of pethidine from local pharmacies. Their discussions with the pharmacists
concerned were reassuring; <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was held in high esteem by them and was
described as ‘ very efficient and confident’. The police report written at the time
concluded:
‘ It would seem from the enquiries made into this matter that there is no
drug abuse by Dr <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>.
* <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> himself uses the spelling ‘ <PERSON>Fredrick</PERSON>’; see, for example, page CO 76 04038 of the scanned documents.
8
The Shipman Inquiry
A watch will be maintained and should anything further come to light
then a further report will be submitted’.
1.6 In early June 1975, it was noticed that a local pharmaceutical company was regularly
supplying to the pharmacy at Boots the Chemists in <LOCATION>Todmorden</LOCATION> abnormally large
amounts of pethidine for injection. Those amounts were accounted for by <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s
written orders on behalf of the practice and by prescriptions for the drug issued by him.
As a consequence of this discovery, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was interviewed by two <ORGANIZATION>Home Office</ORGANIZATION>
drugs inspectors and a detective constable from the <ORGANIZATION>West Yorkshire Police</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>
offered ready explanations for the amount of pethidine he had obtained and denied that
he was abusing the drug. However, deficiencies were found in the controlled drugs
documentation held by the practice; in particular, there was no register recording the
supply of pethidine to patients from the surgery stocks, as required by law. It appeared
to <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s interviewers that some of the ampoules of pethidine, which he had
obtained on written requisition for the practice, were unaccounted for but, without a
register of supplies, this could not be confirmed.
1.7 Because of the deficiencies in procedures which had been revealed at the interview, a
<ORGANIZATION>Home Office</ORGANIZATION> drugs inspector, Mr <PERSON>Donald McIntosh</PERSON>, who has since died, visited the
practice in early August 1975, saw all the partners, including <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>, and advised
them on the institution of a controlled drugs supply register and the correct procedure
for destroying controlled drugs. No further action was taken at that stage, although
Mr <PERSON>McIntosh</PERSON> expressed his intention of keeping the case under review. He requested
from the police a further report in about six months’ time, giving details of all controlled
drugs obtained by <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> over that period. In the event, that report was never
prepared, having been overtaken by events.
1.8 Meanwhile, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was experiencing problems with his health. In May 1975, one of
his partners, Dr <PERSON>John Dacre</PERSON>, was called out by <PERSON>Mrs Primrose Shipman</PERSON>, after her
husband had fallen in the bathroom and struck his head. Dr <PERSON>Dacre</PERSON> diagnosed
concussion and referred <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> to the casualty department of one of the local
hospitals. <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s partners recall other occasions when he suffered ‘ blackouts’ or
‘ seizures’; one occurred in the practice car park and another partner, Dr <PERSON>David Bunn</PERSON>,
remembers assisting him on that occasion. <PERSON>Mrs Shipman</PERSON> gave evidence about an
incident when her husband blacked out beside her while she was driving the family car
with him as a passenger. According to another of his partners, Dr <PERSON>Michael Grieve</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> suffered several blackouts in front of patients in the surgery waiting room.
1.9 Because of his blackouts, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was referred to Dr <PERSON>Philip Humberstone</PERSON>, a consultant
physician at the <ORGANIZATION>Halifax Royal Infirmary</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was seen there on 18th August 1975
and it seems that a diagnosis of idiopathic epilepsy (i.e. epilepsy of unidentified origin)
was made.
1.10 At some time during 1975, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was either advised, or himself decided, to stop
driving and, from that time, he relied on his wife to drive him when he visited patients at
their homes. It is not known precisely when this arrangement began. <PERSON>Mrs Shipman</PERSON>’s
recollection was that the blackouts began ‘ not many months’ before they left <ORGANIZATION>Todmorden</ORGANIZATION>
9
in late 1975. She thought that she had been driving him around for only a matter of
weeks before he ceased to practise in <LOCATION>Todmorden</LOCATION>.
Discovery
1.11 In late September 1975, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s partners discovered that he was abusing pethidine
and had been obtaining the drug illicitly to feed his habit. He had obtained large
quantities of pethidine on written requisition, ostensibly for practice use; these quantities
could not be accounted for and it was plain that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> had taken them for his own
use. His partners confronted <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>, who admitted that he was abusing pethidine
and, after unsuccessfully trying to persuade his colleagues to assist him in continuing to
obtain supplies of the drug illegally, tendered his resignation from the practice. Although
he later withdrew that resignation, his partners took legal advice and eventually
succeeded in dismissing him from the practice.
1.12 <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was immediately admitted to the <ORGANIZATION>Halifax Royal Infirmary</ORGANIZATION> under the care of
Dr <PERSON>Humberstone</PERSON>, who quickly referred him to a consultant psychiatrist, Dr <PERSON>Hugo Milne</PERSON>.
Dr <PERSON>Milne</PERSON> arranged for <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s voluntary admission to The Retreat, a private hospital
in <LOCATION>York</LOCATION>, specialising in the treatment of psychiatric disorders. There, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was
placed under the care of Dr <PERSON>R W Bryson</PERSON>, consultant psychiatrist. Both psychiatrists later
notified the <ORGANIZATION>Home Office</ORGANIZATION> that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> should be registered as a drug addict.
1.13 <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was successfully withdrawn from pethidine, following which he was diagnosed
as suffering from a moderately severe depressive or melancholic state. He was treated
with antidepressant medication, which appeared to effect a great improvement in his
condition. He was discharged from The Retreat on 30th December 1975, with advice to
continue under psychiatric supervision for several years.
Criminal Proceedings
1.14 Meanwhile, the latest developments had been immediately notified by <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s
partners to the <ORGANIZATION>Home Office Drugs Inspectorate</ORGANIZATION> which, in turn, had informed the police.
On 28th November 1975, <PERSON>Mr McIntosh</PERSON>, together with Detective Sergeant <PERSON>George
McKeating</PERSON>, from the <ORGANIZATION>West Yorkshire Police Drugs Squad</ORGANIZATION>, interviewed <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> at The
Retreat. Initially, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> refused to speak to the police officer but quickly changed his
mind and gave what his interviewers took to be a full account of his criminal activities.
He admitted using a variety of deceptions to obtain pethidine for his own consumption
which he claimed had risen, by the time of his discovery, to 600 to 700mg a day. He
said that he had started taking pethidine about 18 months previously (that is in about
May 1974) when he became depressed because he did not get on with his partners.
It should be said that his partners do not agree that there was any friction within the
practice; they were never asked for their response to <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s assertion and, indeed,
say that they were unaware that he was to be prosecuted until they read about the court
proceedings in the local newspaper.
1.15 <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> then made a detailed written statement, setting out his account of what had
occurred. In the course of that statement, he wrote:
10
The Shipman Inquiry
‘ I have no future intention to return to General Practice or work in a
situation where I could obtain supplies of pethidine’.
1.16 On 13th February 1976, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> appeared at the <ORGANIZATION>Halifax Magistrates’ Court</ORGANIZATION>, where he
pleaded guilty to eight specimen charges: three offences of obtaining ten ampoules of
100mg pethidine by deception, three of unlawfully possessing pethidine and two of
forging a prescription. He asked for 74 further offences to be taken into consideration.
Unfortunately, no list of those further offences survives; the police and court files, which
would have contained such a list, have now been destroyed. However, it is clear from
contemporaneous press reports that 67 of the 74 offences concerned the obtaining of
pethidine by deception. <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was fined £75 on each charge, £600 in all, and
ordered to pay compensation of £58.78 to the <ORGANIZATION>NHS Family Practitioners Committee</ORGANIZATION>.
A New Job
1.17 By the time of his conviction, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> had already started a new job. On 2nd February
1976, he had commenced employment with the <ORGANIZATION>Durham Area Health Authority</ORGANIZATION> as a
clinical medical officer at the <LOCATION>Newton Aycliffe Health Centre</LOCATION>. He told his prospective
employers of his previous problem with drugs and of the fact that he was facing criminal
proceedings and possible disciplinary action by the GMC. Having discussed his case
with the psychiatrists who had been treating him, the <ORGANIZATION>Health Authority</ORGANIZATION> offered him the
post on condition that he continue to have follow-up care from a psychiatrist. <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>
had no access to controlled drugs in the course of his new employment.
1.18 Meanwhile, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s health problems had resolved and he had ceased to suffer the
blackouts or seizures which had affected him during his time in <LOCATION>Todmorden</LOCATION>. With
hindsight, it is clear that those episodes were a product of his pethidine abuse, rather
than a manifestation of epilepsy. His wife believes that he began to drive again in
about March 1976. He was still under the care of Dr <PERSON>Milne</PERSON> in April 1976 but it is not
known how much longer this psychiatric supervision continued, as Dr <PERSON>Milne</PERSON>’s records
have not survived.
Possible Disciplinary Proceedings
1.19 <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s convictions at the Magistrates’ Court were reported to the <ORGANIZATION>GMC</ORGANIZATION>, which then
had to decide whether to take disciplinary action against him to remove or restrict his
registration as a doctor. Following the procedure then in force, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s case was
automatically referred to the <ORGANIZATION>Penal Cases Committee</ORGANIZATION>, whose task it was to decide, on
the basis of written evidence and submissions, whether the case should be referred for
inquiry to the <ORGANIZATION>GMC Disciplinary Committee</ORGANIZATION>.
1.20 <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s case came before the <ORGANIZATION>Penal Cases Committee</ORGANIZATION>, which had before it reports
from Dr <PERSON>Bryson</PERSON> and Dr <PERSON>Milne</PERSON>, the consultant psychiatrists who had treated <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>.
There was also a letter of support from Dr <PERSON>Michael O’Brien</PERSON>, Area Medical Officer of the
<ORGANIZATION>Durham Area Health Authority</ORGANIZATION>; the letter stated that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> ‘ had settled well into his
new employment’ and was ‘ well received by both patients and professional colleagues
alike’, with no evidence to suggest any recurrence of ‘ his former difficulties’.
11
1.21 On 28th April 1976, the <ORGANIZATION>Penal Cases Committee</ORGANIZATION> of the <ORGANIZATION>GMC</ORGANIZATION> determined that no inquiry
into <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s case should be held by the <ORGANIZATION>Disciplinary Committee</ORGANIZATION> and that the case
could, therefore, be concluded. Subsequently, a letter was sent to <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>, part of
which reads as follows:
‘ The <ORGANIZATION>Committee</ORGANIZATION> instructed me to inform you that they take a grave view
of offences arising out of an abuse of drugs and of offences involving
dishonesty… You would therefore be wise to assume that, if
information relating to any further conviction of a similar nature should
be received by the <ORGANIZATION>Council</ORGANIZATION>, a charge would then be formulated against
you on the basis of both the earlier and the later convictions and
referred to the <ORGANIZATION>Disciplinary Committee of the Council</ORGANIZATION> for inquiry’.
The <ORGANIZATION>GMC</ORGANIZATION> informed the <ORGANIZATION>Home Office</ORGANIZATION> of its decision by a letter dated 3rd May 1976.
1.22 Following <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s conviction for drugs offences under the Misuse of Drugs Act 1971,
the Home Secretary had power under that Act to make a direction pursuant to section
12, prohibiting <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> from having in his possession, prescribing, administering or
otherwise dealing with such controlled drugs as were specified in the direction. In the
event, the <ORGANIZATION>Home Office</ORGANIZATION> officials who dealt with the case decided that no such direction
should be given. In reaching that decision, they appear to have been influenced by the
view expressed by the police that there was no evidence that any of <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s patients
had suffered as a result of his obtaining of pethidine and also by the decision of the
<ORGANIZATION>GMC</ORGANIZATION> not to take disciplinary proceedings against <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>.
The Move to <ORGANIZATION>Donneybrook</ORGANIZATION>
1.23 <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was, therefore, free to pursue his medical career when and where he chose.
In 1977, he responded to an advertisement which had been placed in a medical
publication by a seven doctor practice in <LOCATION>Hyde</LOCATION>, a former mill town which has, over the
years, been subsumed into the <LOCATION>Greater Manchester</LOCATION> conurbation. The <ORGANIZATION>Donneybrook</ORGANIZATION>
practice was seeking a new doctor to replace one who was leaving to work in industry.
At interview, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> told members of the practice about his previous abuse of
pethidine and his convictions. He referred them to one of the psychiatrists who had
treated him and who would be able to give them details about his condition.
1.24 One of the doctors at the practice spoke to the psychiatrist named by <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> (it is not
clear whether this was Dr <PERSON>Milne</PERSON> or Dr <PERSON>Bryson</PERSON>, although it seems likely to have been the
latter) and also to officials at the <ORGANIZATION>GMC</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Home Office</ORGANIZATION>. He was assured by the
psychiatrist that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was not, in his opinion, suffering from any mental health
problems which would interfere with his work as a general practitioner and he was
informed (correctly) by the <ORGANIZATION>GMC</ORGANIZATION> and the Home Office that there were no restrictions in
force which would affect <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s use of controlled drugs. Once that information had
been obtained, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was invited to join the practice, starting on 1st October 1977.
1.25 <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> stayed at the <ORGANIZATION>Donneybrook</ORGANIZATION> practice for over 14 years. He was hard-working,
apparently dedicated and popular with his patients. He was active in introducing new
ideas to the practice and also became involved in organisations outside the practice.
12
The Shipman Inquiry
For several years, he was an area surgeon for the local <ORGANIZATION>St John Ambulance</ORGANIZATION>; he was a
member of the (then) <ORGANIZATION>Family Practitioners Committee</ORGANIZATION> and, later, secretary of the
<ORGANIZATION>Tameside Local Medical Committee</ORGANIZATION>.
1.26 In 1991, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> told his colleagues at <LOCATION>Donneybrook</LOCATION> that he was intending to leave the
practice; the ostensible reasons for this were <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s dislike of the computer system,
which had been introduced in 1989 to record patient details, and his disagreement
with the proposed scheme of fundholding. With hindsight, these stated reasons for
his departure make little sense since, once in his own practice, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> embraced
enthusiastically the use of computers and became chairman of the local users’ group for
Micro-Doc, a software system developed especially for doctors. Moreover, in 1995, he
joined the <ORGANIZATION>Tameside Consortium</ORGANIZATION> (South) for the specific purpose of fundholding.
It seems that, even at the time, at least some members of the <ORGANIZATION>Donneybrook</ORGANIZATION> practice
believed that he might have had other reasons for leaving. One describes <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> as
tending to be ‘ individualistic’ in his approach and says that he ‘ could become irritated
if confronted by any other of the doctors and other staff members’. According to him,
the assumption at the time was that these features of his personality might have led
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> to prefer single-handed practice. At his trial, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> claimed that he left
because the other doctors were not as committed to fundholding as he was. It seems
also that, towards the end of his time at the <ORGANIZATION>Donneybrook</ORGANIZATION> practice, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s
relationships with at least one member of the staff there had deteriorated badly.
The Market Street Surgery
1.27 Whatever the real reasons for his move, from 1st January 1992, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> ran a singlehanded
practice from within <ORGANIZATION>Donneybrook House</ORGANIZATION> until his new surgery was ready in
August 1992. He then moved to premises at 21 Market Street, <PERSON>Hyde</PERSON>. He took with him
several members of staff from the <LOCATION>Donneybrook</LOCATION> practice and, to the annoyance and
financial detriment of his former partners, his patient list. The parting was acrimonious
and was followed by lengthy negotiations between solicitors to settle the financial
arrangements consequent upon <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s departure.
1.28 For the next six years, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s practice appeared to flourish. He enjoyed a high
reputation in <PERSON>Hyde</PERSON> as an attentive, caring doctor. A major reason for his popularity was
his willingness to visit his elderly patients at home. One witness described his mother’s
delight at being accepted onto <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s patient list; it was, he said, ‘ as though she
had won the lottery’. Many elderly people were persuaded to join <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s practice by
friends or family members who were impressed by the quality of the care which they
received from him. <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> did not have space on his patient list to accommodate all
those who wished to join it and, by the time of his arrest, he was actively attempting to
recruit a partner to share his workload and enable the practice to take on more patients.
1.29 <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> and his staff performed regular medical audits, which impressed the <ORGANIZATION>Health
Authority’s Audit Group</ORGANIZATION>, and the practice was generally regarded as being innovative
and advanced. Some indication of the high esteem in which <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was held emerges
from a <ORGANIZATION>Health Authority</ORGANIZATION> document dating from late December 1997. An issue had arisen
about access to patient records and the <ORGANIZATION>Health Authority</ORGANIZATION>’s solicitor had advised
13
Ms <PERSON>Andrea Horsfall</PERSON>, the deputy complaints manager, to contact a local general
practitioner and ascertain whether he or she was aware of recent guidance issued by
the <ORGANIZATION>British Medical Association</ORGANIZATION>. Ms <PERSON>Horsfall</PERSON> spoke to Dr <PERSON>Alan Banks</PERSON>, then Assistant
Director of <ORGANIZATION>Primary Care and Medical Adviser</ORGANIZATION> to the <ORGANIZATION>Health Authority</ORGANIZATION>. Her note of that
conversation records:
‘ Asked A. Banks which GP I should ring. He suggested Dr <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> as
he is apparantly (sic) very uptodate (sic) on all the latest information/
advice’.
1.30 In addition, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was active in local medical politics and an enthusiastic member,
latterly treasurer, of the local branch of the <ORGANIZATION>Small Practices Association</ORGANIZATION>. Although there
were people who regarded him as arrogant, sometimes overbearing, the majority of his
patients, his staff and other professionals with whom he came into contact appear to
have held him in high esteem and to have believed that the health and welfare of his
patients were his main priority. When giving evidence to the Inquiry in May 2002,
Mr <PERSON>Nigel Reynolds</PERSON>, widower of the late Dr <PERSON>Linda Reynolds</PERSON>, observed that, in 1998,
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was quite simply perceived as ‘ the best doctor in <PERSON>Hyde</PERSON>’.
The Police Investigation of March 1998
1.31 By March of that year, however, certain people in <PERSON>Hyde</PERSON> had begun to feel concern at the
number of <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s elderly patients who were dying in curiously similar
circumstances. After discussion with her colleagues, <PERSON>Dr Reynolds</PERSON>, a partner in the
nearby <LOCATION>Brooke Practice</LOCATION>, alerted the Coroner for the <LOCATION>Greater Manchester South District</LOCATION>
(‘ the <LOCATION>South Manchester</LOCATION> Coroner’), Mr <PERSON>John Pollard</PERSON>, to the concerns felt by herself and
others. Mr <PERSON>Pollard</PERSON> initiated a limited police investigation, during which the police sought
the assistance of the <ORGANIZATION>West Pennine Health Authority</ORGANIZATION>. At the conclusion of that
investigation, the police officer who conducted it, Detective Inspector <PERSON>David Smith</PERSON>,
decided that there was no evidence to substantiate the concerns which had been
expressed by Dr <PERSON>Reynolds</PERSON> to the Coroner. No further action was, therefore, taken.
1.32 The conduct of the March 1998 investigation and its outcome have been fully examined
by the Inquiry in the course of oral hearings held between May and July 2002.
The Inquiry’s findings as to the adequacy of the investigation will be published in
due course.
The Death of Mrs <PERSON>Kathleen Grundy</PERSON>
1.33 Mrs <PERSON>Kathleen Grundy</PERSON> died on 24th June 1998. She was <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s patient and he
certified the cause of her death as ‘ old age’. Despite her 81 years, <PERSON>Mrs Grundy</PERSON> had
enjoyed good health and her death was sudden and unexpected. She was buried at
<LOCATION>Hyde Chapel</LOCATION>.
14
The Shipman Inquiry
1.34 <PERSON>Mrs Grundy</PERSON>’s daughter, <PERSON>Mrs Angela Woodruff</PERSON>, was a practising solicitor who, ever since
she had qualified, had conducted any necessary legal work on her mother’s behalf.
In 1986, she had drawn up <PERSON>Mrs Grundy</PERSON>’s will, by which <PERSON>Mrs Grundy</PERSON> had made her
daughter the sole beneficiary to her substantial estate. Following <PERSON>Mrs Grundy</PERSON>’s death,
<PERSON>Mrs Woodruff</PERSON> became aware of the existence of what purported to be a new will; this
was dated 9th June 1998 and had been sent, together with a covering letter apparently
signed by <PERSON>Mrs Grundy</PERSON>, to a firm of <PERSON>Hyde</PERSON> solicitors very shortly before <PERSON>Mrs Grundy</PERSON>’s
death. Those same solicitors, to whom <PERSON>Mrs Grundy</PERSON> was not known, subsequently
received a letter from a person signing himself or herself ‘ <PERSON>J. Smith</PERSON>’ or ‘ <PERSON>S. Smith</PERSON>’,
informing them of <PERSON>Mrs Grundy</PERSON>’s death. The new will left <PERSON>Mrs Grundy</PERSON>’s entire estate
to <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>. A copy of the will and letters can be seen at the end of this Chapter.
Investigating <PERSON>Mrs Grundy</PERSON>’s Death
1.35 <PERSON>Mrs Woodruff</PERSON> was immediately suspicious about the new will and her suspicions
deepened after she had visited and spoken to the two patients of <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> whose
signatures appeared on the will as witnesses. On 24th July 1998, she reported her
suspicions to the police in <LOCATION>Warwickshire</LOCATION>, where she lived. The matter was passed to the
<ORGANIZATION>Greater Manchester Police</ORGANIZATION> for investigation and it was quickly realised that the doctor
who was the beneficiary of <PERSON>Mrs Grundy</PERSON>’s new will was the same doctor who had been
the subject of a police investigation only a few months earlier.
1.36 A warrant for the exhumation of <PERSON>Mrs Grundy</PERSON>’s body was obtained from the <LOCATION>South
Manchester</LOCATION> Coroner and the exhumation took place on 1st August 1998. On the same
day, the police executed warrants to search <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s surgery and home address.
A typewriter and <PERSON>Mrs Grundy</PERSON>’s medical records were seized from the surgery. On
3rd August 1998, Detective Chief Superintendent (then Detective Superintendent)
<PERSON>Bernard Postles</PERSON> was appointed Senior Investigating Officer and a major incident
investigation began.
1.37 A post-mortem examination of <PERSON>Mrs Grundy</PERSON>’s body failed to establish the cause of her
death and a decision was taken to carry out toxicological tests. On 14th August 1998,
the police were told that initial tests carried out at the <LOCATION>North West Forensic Science
Laboratory</LOCATION> had shown the presence of an opiate, possibly morphine, in <PERSON>Mrs Grundy</PERSON>’s
body. Further tests were to be carried out to confirm the type and levels of opiate
present.
1.38 Also on 14th August 1998, an inspector from the <ORGANIZATION>Home Office Drugs Inspectorate</ORGANIZATION>,
together with a chemist inspector from the <ORGANIZATION>Greater Manchester Police</ORGANIZATION>, visited <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>
at his surgery and interviewed him in connection with his use of controlled drugs. Prior
to that visit, on 10th August, the <ORGANIZATION>Home Office</ORGANIZATION> inspector informed the police that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>
had previous convictions. This was the first time that the <ORGANIZATION>Greater Manchester Police</ORGANIZATION>
became aware that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> had a criminal record. Enquiries were then made and the
nature of the previous convictions established.
1.39 Meanwhile, the police had decided to re-examine the 19 deaths certified by <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>, of
which they had become aware during the March 1998 investigation. They began to
interview family members to ascertain whether they had any concerns about the
15
circumstances of the deaths. Later in August, the investigation was widened to include
a further nine deaths.
1.40 On 26th August 1998, the police were informed of the opinion of Mr <PERSON>Michael Hall</PERSON>, a
forensic document examiner, that the signatures on <PERSON>Mrs Grundy</PERSON>’s new will had been
forged and the will itself had probably been typed on the typewriter which had been
seized from <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s surgery.
1.41 On 28th August 1998, <PERSON>Mrs Julie Evans</PERSON>, a forensic scientist, told the police that the levels
of morphine present in Mrs <PERSON>Grundy</PERSON>’s body were consistent with levels which had
previously been known to have caused death by morphine overdose.
1.42 On 7th September 1998, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was arrested on suspicion of the murder of
<PERSON>Mrs Grundy</PERSON>, of attempting to obtain property by deception and of forgery. He was
interviewed in connection with those offences and later charged. The following day, he
appeared before Tameside Magistrates’ Court, when he was remanded in custody.
He has been in custody ever since.
Widening the Investigation
1.43 During September 1998, the bodies of Mrs <PERSON>Joan Melia</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mrs Winifred Mellor</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Mrs Bianka Pomfret</PERSON> were exhumed. On 5th October 1998, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was arrested on
suspicion of their murders and was interviewed; however, the interview had to be
discontinued because <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> became distressed and confused. He was charged
with the three murders on 7th October 1998.
1.44 In October 1998, the bodies of Mrs <PERSON>Marie Quinn</PERSON> and Mrs Ivy Lomas were exhumed.
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was arrested and interviewed in connection with those deaths on
11th November 1998 but made no comment during the interviews. He was charged with
both murders the same day.
1.45 Exhumations of the bodies of Mrs <PERSON>Jean Lilley</PERSON> and Mrs <PERSON>Irene Turner</PERSON> followed in
November 1998 and, following a further ‘ no comment’ interview, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was charged
with their murders on 3rd December 1998.
1.46 On 22nd February 1999, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was charged with the murder of <PERSON>Mrs Muriel Grimshaw</PERSON>,
whose body had been exhumed in December 1998, together with the murders of
Mrs <PERSON>Norah Nuttall</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mrs Kathleen Wagstaff</PERSON>, Miss <PERSON>Maureen Ward</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mrs Pamela Hillier</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Mrs Maria West</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mrs Lizzie Adams</PERSON>, all of whom had been cremated.
Suspension from Practice
1.47 The police had been attempting for some time to prevent <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> from continuing to
practise. They had informed the <ORGANIZATION>GMC</ORGANIZATION> of the position in August 1998 but were told that
the GMC could do nothing until <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> had been convicted of an offence. On
18th August, the <ORGANIZATION>West Pennine Health Authority</ORGANIZATION> contacted the <ORGANIZATION>NHS Tribunal</ORGANIZATION>, which had
power to suspend him, but a hearing by the <ORGANIZATION>Tribunal</ORGANIZATION> could not be arranged before
29th September. After that hearing, the <ORGANIZATION>Tribunal</ORGANIZATION>’s decision to suspend <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> from
practice was not communicated to the <ORGANIZATION>Health Authority</ORGANIZATION> until 15th October. The Health
16
The <ORGANIZATION>Shipman Inquiry
Authority</ORGANIZATION> was able to take control of the practice only after the expiration of the period
for an appeal against that decision, on 29th October 1998.
The Criminal Trial
1.48 At <ORGANIZATION>Shipman</ORGANIZATION>’s trial, which opened on 5th October 1999, he pleaded not guilty to the 15
counts of murder against him and to one count of forging <PERSON>Mrs Grundy</PERSON>’s will. On
31st January 2000, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was convicted on all counts. He was sentenced to 15 terms
of life imprisonment and, for the forgery, a concurrent term of four years’ imprisonment.
When sentencing <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>, the trial judge, <PERSON>Mr Justice Forbes</PERSON>, stated that his
recommendation to the Home Secretary would be that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> should spend the
remainder of his days in prison.
The End of <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s Professional Career
1.49 Following the trial, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was suspended from practice by the <ORGANIZATION>GMC Preliminary
Proceedings Committee</ORGANIZATION> and, on 11th February 2000, his name was erased from the
medical register by the <ORGANIZATION>Professional Conduct Committee</ORGANIZATION> of the GMC.
The Inquests
1.50 In the course of the police investigations, bodies had been exhumed in three cases
which did not form the subject of counts on the indictment at the criminal trial. Inquests
into the deaths of Mrs <PERSON>Sarah Ashworth</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mrs Alice Kitchen</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mrs Elizabeth Mellor</PERSON> had
been opened and adjourned by the <LOCATION>South Manchester</LOCATION> Coroner shortly after the
exhumations; these inquests were concluded in August and September 2000; all three
resulted in verdicts of unlawful killing.
1.51 By the time of the trial, the police had investigated a large number of deaths amongst
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s patients, in addition to the 15 deaths which were the subject of counts on the
indictment and the additional three cases where bodies had been exhumed. Some of
these investigations had been initiated by the police themselves; others had started as a
result of communications from concerned relatives. As a result of their investigations,
the police identified 23 further cases in which they believed that the evidence was
strong enough to justify a prosecution for murder.
1.52 On 18th February 2000, the Director of Public Prosecutions announced that no further
criminal proceedings would be instituted against <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> because of the impossibility
of his having a fair trial after the publicity surrounding his convictions in January 2000.
A further factor was that, since it had been recommended that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> should spend
the rest of his life in prison, no additional punishment would be imposed as a result of
any future conviction.
1.53 In early 2001, the <LOCATION>South Manchester</LOCATION> Coroner sought and obtained from the Home
Secretary a direction to open inquests into the 23 deaths identified by the police,
together with a further death, that of Mr <PERSON>Charles Killan</PERSON>. The inquests were held between
January and April 2001 and concerned the deaths of Mrs <PERSON>Dorothy Andrew</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mrs Irene</PERSON>
17
<PERSON>Berry</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mrs Edith Brady</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mrs Edith Brock</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mrs Elsie Cheetham</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mrs Erla Copeland</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Mrs Lilian Cullen</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mrs Valerie Cuthbert</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mrs Elsie Dean</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mrs Joan Dean</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mrs Doris
Earls</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mrs Elsie Hannible</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mrs Irene Heathcote</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mrs Hilda Hibbert</PERSON>, Mr <PERSON>Charles Killan</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Mrs Bertha Moss</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mrs Nellie Mullen</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mrs Gladys Saunders</PERSON>, Miss <PERSON>Mabel Shawcross</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Mrs Marjorie Waller</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mrs Mary Walls</PERSON>, Miss <PERSON>Ada Warburton</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mrs Amy Whitehead</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Mrs Joyce Woodhead</PERSON>. All resulted in verdicts of unlawful killing, save for the inquests
into the deaths of Mrs <PERSON>Joan Dean</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mrs Marjorie Waller</PERSON>, at the conclusion of which the
Coroner returned open verdicts.
Further Police Investigations
1.54 The publicity surrounding <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s trial and convictions caused more people to
contact the police, concerned about <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s possible involvement in the death of a
family member. By the beginning of 2001, the <ORGANIZATION>Greater Manchester Police</ORGANIZATION> had
investigated 192 deaths. Meanwhile, the <ORGANIZATION>West Yorkshire Police</ORGANIZATION> had carried out
investigations into the deaths of Mr <PERSON>Edward Walker</PERSON> and Mrs <PERSON>Margaret Wilmore</PERSON> in
<LOCATION>Todmorden</LOCATION> and an incident involving Professor <PERSON>Elaine Oswald</PERSON>, who had become
concerned during the criminal trial that she may have been one of <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s
intended victims.
1.55 On 5th January 2001, Professor <PERSON>Richard Baker</PERSON>’s review of <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s practice, which
had been commissioned by the Chief Medical Officer, was published. That review,
which is discussed by Professor <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> in Appendix A to this Report, identified deaths
which he considered suspicious, having examined the cremation forms and/or the
medical records of the deceased. Approximately 60 of those deaths had not previously
been investigated by the police; following publication of the review, the
police proceeded to investigate them, together with others of which they had recently
become aware.
1.56 Professor <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> discovered that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> had issued 22 Medical Certificates of Cause
of Death (MCCDs) during his time in <LOCATION>Todmorden</LOCATION>, including the MCCD relating to the
death of Mr <PERSON>Edward Walker</PERSON>. Following the publication of the review, the <ORGANIZATION>West Yorkshire
Police</ORGANIZATION> investigated the other 21 deaths, as well as nine deaths (including that of
Mrs <PERSON>Margaret Wilmore</PERSON>) which had been certified by the local coroner. They interviewed
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> about the Todmorden deaths at <ORGANIZATION>Halifax Police Station</ORGANIZATION> on 30th April 2001. He
refused to answer their questions.
1.57 All those investigations had been concluded by June 2001, at which time the incident
room was closed and the police investigation scaled down.
The Laming Inquiry
1.58 On 1st February 2000, the day after <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s convictions, the Secretary of <ORGANIZATION>State for
Health</ORGANIZATION>, The Rt. Hon. <PERSON>Alan Milburn</PERSON>, MP, announced in the <ORGANIZATION>House of Commons</ORGANIZATION> the setting
up of an inquiry under the provisions of section 2 of the National Health Service Act
1977, under the chairmanship of Lord <PERSON>Laming</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Tewin</LOCATION>.
18
The Shipman Inquiry
1.59 The Laming Inquiry began its preliminary work but, when it was discovered that it was to
be held in private, that members of the families of the deceased former patients of
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> would not be permitted to hear or read the evidence given to the Inquiry by
statutory and other bodies or individuals, and that families would not be permitted legal
representation, there was widespread dissatisfaction about the form of the Inquiry.
Representations were made to the Secretary of State on behalf of a number of relatives
of <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s known or suspected victims, known collectively as the <ORGANIZATION>Tameside Families
Support Group</ORGANIZATION>. The Secretary of <ORGANIZATION>State</ORGANIZATION> considered his decision afresh but declined to
change it. He stated his reasons for maintaining his stance in a letter dated 12th April
2000, addressed to Ms <PERSON>Ann Alexander</PERSON>, the solicitor representing the Support Group. As
a result, proceedings for judicial review were commenced by the <ORGANIZATION>Support Group</ORGANIZATION> and,
subsequently, by nine media organisations.
1.60 On 20th July 2000, the Divisional Court set aside the Secretary of <ORGANIZATION>State</ORGANIZATION>’s decision of
12th April and remitted the matter for re-determination by him.
1.61 On 21st September 2000, the Secretary of <ORGANIZATION>State</ORGANIZATION> announced that a public inquiry would
be held into the issues surrounding the crimes committed by <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>.
19
The forged will in the name of Mrs <PERSON>Kathleen Grundy</PERSON>, leaving her entire estate to <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>
20
The <ORGANIZATION>Shipman Inquiry
Letter</ORGANIZATION> to a local firm of solicitors, purporting to be from Mrs <PERSON>Kathleen Grundy</PERSON>, sending
them a copy of the forged will for safekeeping
Letter to the solicitors, purporting to be from a friend of <PERSON>Mrs Katheen Grundy</PERSON> called
‘ <PERSON>J. Smith</PERSON>’ or ‘ <PERSON>S. Smith</PERSON>’, informing them of <PERSON>Mrs Grundy</PERSON>’s death
21
CHAPTER TWO
The Inquiry
The Setting Up of the Inquiry
2.1 On 31st January 2001, exactly a year after <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s convictions and following
resolutions in both Houses of <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION>, the Secretary of <ORGANIZATION>State for Health</ORGANIZATION> issued the
instrument of appointment, establishing The <ORGANIZATION>Shipman Inquiry</ORGANIZATION>, giving it the powers
conferred by the Tribunals of Inquiry (Evidence) Act 1921 and appointing me as
Chairman of the Inquiry.
Terms of Reference
2.2 The Terms of Reference of the Inquiry are as follows:
‘ (a) after receiving the existing evidence and hearing such further evidence as
necessary, to consider the extent of <PERSON>Harold Shipman</PERSON>’s unlawful activities;
(b) to enquire into the actions of the statutory bodies, authorities, other
organisations and responsible individuals concerned in the procedures and
investigations which followed the deaths of those of <PERSON>Harold Shipman</PERSON>’s
patients who died in unlawful or suspicious circumstances;
(c) by reference to the case of <PERSON>Harold Shipman</PERSON> to enquire into the performance of
the functions of those statutory bodies, authorities, other organisations and
individuals with responsibility for monitoring primary care provision and the
use of controlled drugs; and
(d) following those enquiries, to recommend what steps, if any, should be taken to
protect patients in the future, and to report its findings to the Secretary of
<ORGANIZATION>State</ORGANIZATION> for the Home Department and to the Secretary of <ORGANIZATION>State for Health</ORGANIZATION>’.
Independence
2.3 Although the Inquiry was set up by <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> at the invitation of the Secretary of <ORGANIZATION>State
for Health</ORGANIZATION> and is funded from the budget of the <ORGANIZATION>Department of Health</ORGANIZATION>, it is wholly
independent of Government.
Starting Work
2.4 The Inquiry was able to take over the offices at <ORGANIZATION>Gateway House</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Manchester</LOCATION> which had
previously been occupied by the Laming Inquiry. Work began immediately on the
collection and assessment of the available evidence; the legal team at first consisted
only of Leading Counsel to the Inquiry, Miss <PERSON>Caroline Swift</PERSON> QC, and the Inquiry’s then
Solicitor, Mr <PERSON>Campbell Kennedy</PERSON>, but they were soon joined by Senior Counsel,
Mr <PERSON>Christopher Melton</PERSON> (who was appointed Queen’s Counsel in April 2001) and Junior
Counsel, Mr <PERSON>Anthony Mazzag</PERSON> and Mr <PERSON>Michael Jones</PERSON>, and by the Deputy Solicitor to the
Inquiry, Miss <PERSON>Ita Langan</PERSON>. In March 2001, Mr <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON> was replaced as Solicitor to the
22
The Shipman Inquiry
Inquiry by Mr <PERSON>Henry Palin</PERSON>. The Secretary to the Inquiry, Mr <PERSON>Andrew Griffiths</PERSON>, established
the administrative team.
2.5 I appointed Dr <PERSON>Aneez Esmail</PERSON>, LRCP MRCS MFPHM PhD to be my Medical Advisor. At
the time of his appointment, Dr <PERSON>Esmail</PERSON> was Head of the <ORGANIZATION>School of Primary Care</ORGANIZATION> at the
<ORGANIZATION>University of Manchester</ORGANIZATION>; he is a practising general practitioner and has also trained in
public health. He has, therefore, been able to advise me on matters relating to the
organisation of general practice and on medical issues relating to some of the individual
deaths which I have had to consider.
Deciding How to Proceed
2.6 The first of the Inquiry’s Terms of Reference required it to consider the extent of
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s unlawful activities. It seemed to me that this could be done in two ways. The
first possible approach was for me to look at the totality of the evidence relating to the
deaths which <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was known to have caused or was suspected of causing, and
take a broad and general view of his criminality. Alternatively, I could instruct the legal
team to investigate every suspicious or potentially suspicious death in which <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>
may have been involved as thoroughly as possible and then, on the basis of the
evidence collected, reach a decision in the case of each individual death as to whether
or not <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was responsible for it.
2.7 Having considered the matter carefully and discussed it with the legal team, I decided
on the latter course. My reasons for doing so were these:
• There were hundreds of people who were in a state of uncertainty and distress, not
knowing whether their relatives had died a natural death or been killed by
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>; there was a strong feeling that it was only by knowing the truth that they
would be able to begin to come to terms with their shock and grief.
• Whilst it was anticipated that some of the deaths would be the subject of coroner’s
inquests in the future, not all those deaths had been fully investigated by the
police, and, if the Inquiry did not undertake further investigations, the evidence
relating to those deaths would remain incomplete. Also, it was unlikely that
inquests would be held into all the deaths which the Inquiry would investigate.
• It seemed to me essential that, before I went on to consider whether, and, if so, in
what respects, there had been failures in systems or on the part of individuals or
statutory or other bodies, which had allowed <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> to commit murder
unchecked, I had to be able to form an accurate and authoritative view as to the
number of people he had killed and the period over which – and the
circumstances in which – the killings were perpetrated. Only by making decisions
about <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s responsibility for individual deaths would I be able to form such
a view.
2.8 In deciding that individual deaths should be investigated, I did, of course, anticipate
that a great deal of work would be involved in the collection and analysis of evidence
relating to the individual deaths and, indeed, in the decision-making process itself. In
the event, the Inquiry’s decision to investigate a large number of deaths which had not
23
previously been investigated by the police has made the task an even more formidable
one than I had anticipated. However, the reaction of many of the family members
concerned, and their evident relief at being made aware for the first time of the full
circumstances surrounding their relatives’ deaths, has persuaded me that my decision
was the right one.
The First Report
2.9 It was plainly logical that the determination of <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s guilt in respect of individual
deaths should be the subject of the first phase of the Inquiry. Thus, when the Inquiry
published its List of Issues in March 2001, the issues to be considered in Phase One
were identified as:
‘ …how many patients <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> killed, the means employed and the
period over which the killings took place’.
2.10 Because of my desire to bring to an end, wherever possible, the uncertainty of many
family members as to whether or not <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> killed their relatives, I decided that the
Inquiry should publish a First Report, setting out my findings as to <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s guilt in
respect of all those deaths which the Inquiry legal team placed before me for decision.
Those findings can be found in Volumes Two to Six of this Report.
The Application of the Coroners Act 1988
2.11 In February 2000, the <LOCATION>South Manchester</LOCATION> Coroner sought a direction from the then Home
Secretary, The Rt. Hon. Mr <PERSON>Jack Straw</PERSON>, MP, to open inquests into all the deaths (not
previously the subject of the criminal trial or past or planned inquests) which had been
reported to him by the police. Such a direction was required because the bodies had
been cremated.
2.12 The Inquiry legal team was concerned that, if the Coroner were to proceed to hold full
inquests into those deaths, this would involve a duplication of the work of the Inquiry in
investigating and making decisions in respect of those deaths. There was also the risk
of inconsistency as between the Coroner’s verdicts and my own findings.
2.13 Accordingly, I invited the Lord Chancellor to exercise his powers under the provisions of
Section 17A of the Coroners Act 1988 and to require that the inquests, when opened,
should be adjourned pending publication of the findings of the Inquiry.
2.14 On 30th April 2001, the Home Secretary directed the Coroner to open inquests into 262
deaths and, on 4th May 2001, the Lord Chancellor wrote to Mr <PERSON>Pollard</PERSON>, requiring that
those inquests, once opened, should be immediately adjourned in the absence of any
exceptional reason why this should not be done.
2.15 On 18th May 2001, the Coroner opened inquests into 232 deaths, which inquests were
then adjourned. The disparity in the numbers of inquests (i.e. between 262 and 232)
was caused, according to the Coroner, by the fact that the original list included a
number of deaths which had already been the subject of criminal convictions or
inquests.
24
The <ORGANIZATION>Shipman Inquiry</ORGANIZATION>
2.16 Following publication of this First Report, my findings in the 232 cases will be
communicated to the Coroner; he will then forward certificates to the register office, with
a view to re-registration of the deaths with causes of death consistent with my findings,
without the need for the inquests to be resumed. In those cases where no inquest has
yet been opened but where it appears that, on the basis of my findings, re-registration of
the death is appropriate, I anticipate that inquests will be opened and adjourned under
the provisions of Section 17A of the 1988 Act and that my findings will be forwarded to
the register office in the same way.
Identifying the Deaths to be Investigated
2.17 The first task confronting the legal team was to identify all those deaths which should be
examined by the Inquiry. A database was created, on which details of every death
known to the Inquiry were recorded.
<PERSON>HOLMES</PERSON>
2.18 The starting point was the huge amount of information which had already been collected
by the police. The <ORGANIZATION>Greater Manchester Police</ORGANIZATION> gave the Inquiry immediate access to
their database, the Home Office Large Major Enquiry System (‘ <PERSON>HOLMES</PERSON>’), on which
appeared details of, and evidence relating to, all the deaths which had been
investigated by them and by the <ORGANIZATION>West Yorkshire Police</ORGANIZATION>, together with details of some
deaths which had not been investigated. The information contained on <PERSON>HOLMES</PERSON> was
updated from time to time until the police incident room was closed, and the
investigation scaled down, in June 2001.
Professor <PERSON>Baker</PERSON>’s Audit
2.19 In the course of the research involved in his review, Professor <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> had identified
virtually every death in <LOCATION>Todmorden</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Hyde</PERSON> for which <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> had signed the MCCD.
Inevitably, a small number of such deaths were missed, either because they were
registered outside the district or by reason of human error. However, the Inquiry has
been able to identify most, if not all, of the ‘ missed’ deaths by checking through
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s books of used MCCDs, in which the counterfoils remain. Professor <PERSON>Baker</PERSON>
provided to the Inquiry a list of every death which he had identified; many of them also
appeared on HOLMES but the remainder were added to the Inquiry’s database, for
scrutiny by the Inquiry team. Those additional deaths which the Inquiry had identified
from the MCCD counterfoils were also put on the database.
Expressions of Concern
2.20 Any death in respect of which a relative, friend or other member of the public expressed
concern to the Inquiry was considered by the legal team. Sometimes, there was no
known connection between the death and <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>, and the caller just wanted to
exclude the possibility that he might have been involved; in that event, the legal team
was able to reassure him or her and close the case immediately. In other cases,
however, the circumstances gave rise to a possibility that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> may have been
responsible for the death and, in such cases, a full investigation was undertaken.
25
Coroner’s Cases
2.21 There is a perception among the public that all deaths automatically come to the
attention of the local coroner. In fact, that is not the case – the coroner only becomes
aware of deaths which are specifically referred to him, or about which his advice is
sought. The majority of deaths proceed to registration, and thereafter to burial or
cremation of the body, without the intervention of the coroner, the cause of death having
been certified by the deceased’s general practitioner or a hospital doctor. Initially,
therefore, the police investigation centred on deaths which had been certified by
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>, rather than those which had been referred to the coroner.
2.22 Following publication of Professor <PERSON>Baker</PERSON>’s review, however, there was considerable
concern in <LOCATION>Todmorden</LOCATION> about <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s possible involvement, not only in deaths which
had been certified by him, but also in deaths which had been referred to and certified
by the coroner. In response to that concern, the <ORGANIZATION>West Yorkshire Police</ORGANIZATION> considered 81
deaths which had been referred to the Coroner during <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s time in <LOCATION>Todmorden</LOCATION>
and carried out detailed investigations into nine of those deaths where there was
thought to be a real possibility of involvement by <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>.
2.23 The Inquiry has examined the Coroner’s files for the 81 deaths considered by the police.
The files contained post-mortem examination reports and factual summaries provided to
the Coroner by the police at the time of the death. The Inquiry legal team confirmed that
there was evidence of involvement by <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> only in the nine cases already identified
by the police. One additional file was opened but was closed when the hospital records
of the deceased person in question revealed that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was not involved in the
death. One of the nine cases involved the death of a newborn child. There is no question
of deliberate killing in that case, although it has been suggested that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> may have
provided inadequate medical care. As such, that death falls outside the Inquiry’s Terms
of Reference for Phase One. I have given decisions in the remaining eight cases and am
satisfied, on the basis of the available evidence (including expert forensic pathological
evidence), that six were natural deaths. In the seventh, there was inadequate evidence
to enable me to reach a decision and the eighth I regarded as suspicious, without being
able to come to any positive conclusion about <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s guilt.
2.24 The legal team considered for some time whether or not it should perform a similar
exercise in relation to the deaths which had been referred to the <LOCATION>South Manchester</LOCATION>
Coroner during <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s time in <PERSON>Hyde</PERSON>. It was recognised that this would be a far
bigger task than in <LOCATION>Todmorden</LOCATION>, involving as it would the examination of an estimated
52,500 files, covering a period of 21 years. It was also recognised that the Inquiry had to
balance the need to obtain the fullest possible information about deaths occurring
during <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s professional life against the time and resources which a full review of
the <ORGANIZATION>South Manchester Coroner</ORGANIZATION>’s files would take. With those considerations in mind, I
decided that, in the interests of completeness, a search of the Coroner’s files should be
undertaken, with a view to identifying those deaths which were or might be connected
with <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>.
2.25 As a result of the search which ensued, 136 deaths in which <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> had some
involvement, usually as the deceased’s general practitioner, were identified. The
26
The <ORGANIZATION>Shipman Inquiry</ORGANIZATION>
majority of the deaths raised no suspicion, once the circumstances were examined, and
those cases were closed. A number of the deaths identified from the Coroner’s files had
come to the Inquiry’s attention by other means and were already the subject of
investigation. However, a small proportion were deaths of which the Inquiry had no
previous knowledge and these were made the subject of further investigation by the
legal team.
2.26 In the event, I have found that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was responsible for only three deaths which had
been referred to the Coroner immediately after the death (other than by means of an
informal telephone query such as that made in the case of Mrs <PERSON>Kathleen Grundy</PERSON>); in one
of those cases (that of Mr <PERSON>Charles Barlow</PERSON>), there was a post-mortem examination which
revealed an apparently natural cause of death. In another (that of Mr <PERSON>John Stone</PERSON>), the
Coroner issued a Form 100A, indicating that there had been no post-mortem
examination and that he did not consider it necessary to hold an inquest. The third
patient, <PERSON>Mrs Renate Overton</PERSON>, died on 21st April 1995. She had remained in a persistent
vegetative state for 14 months, following an injection administered by <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> in
February 1994. After a post-mortem examination without inquest, Mr <PERSON>Peter Revington</PERSON>,
who was then the <LOCATION>South Manchester</LOCATION> Coroner, certified that <PERSON>Mrs Overton</PERSON> had died as a
result of natural causes. I have found that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> unlawfully killed <PERSON>Mrs Overton</PERSON>.
2.27 It is plain that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> made every effort to ensure that deaths for which he was
responsible did not come to the coroner’s attention and, as is evident from my
decisions, he developed many techniques by which he was able to prevent them from
doing so.
The Deaths Investigated
2.28 In all, the Inquiry has investigated 887 deaths which were, initially at least, believed to
have some connection with <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>. I have given written decisions in respect of 493 of
these deaths and one incident involving a living person; the remaining 394 cases have
been closed without a decision having been made. It is necessary to explain why.
2.29 As soon as the legal team began to consider the deaths which had been recorded on
the Inquiry database, it was evident that some were completely unconnected with
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>. A number of people, listed on <PERSON>HOLMES</PERSON> as ‘ deceased’, proved to be potential
witnesses who had died, or were deceased relatives of persons whose deaths were
being investigated, but who had not themselves had any dealings with <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>. There
was obviously no point in considering those deaths further and the files relating to them
were closed.
2.30 Similarly, there were a number of deceased patients of <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> whose medical records
had been found at his home and whose details appeared on <PERSON>HOLMES</PERSON>. The Inquiry team
at first suspected that the mere fact that records relating to a particular patient were
found at <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s home might mean that the death of that patient should automatically
be regarded as sinister. However, after the legal team had spent some time looking
specifically at such cases, it became clear that no particular significance could be
attached to the fact that a patient’s records had been found at <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s home.
Consequently, while some of the deaths merited further investigation, there were many
27
others where no cause for suspicion arose. Some of the patients concerned had died in
hospital after a significant period of in-patient treatment, others had died abroad or
suffered an accident. Again, those cases could be closed, in the knowledge that
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was not responsible for the deaths.
2.31 Sometimes, it was only when further evidence was obtained – evidence from a family
witness, for example, to the effect that the deceased person had remained conscious
and apparently well for several hours after <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s most recent visit – that it became
plain that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> could not have caused the death. Such cases were, therefore,
closed at that stage.
2.32 The preliminary view of the Inquiry legal team was that I should give a written decision:
• in the case of all deaths where the Inquiry’s investigations revealed real suspicion
as to whether <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was responsible for the death;
• in all cases where a family, friend or other member of the public had expressed a
real concern about the circumstances of the death and where that concern related
to potentially unlawful activity and was, therefore, within the Inquiry’s Terms of
Reference; this excluded allegations of incompetence, poor service or clinical
negligence;
• in the case of all deaths which had been assessed by Professor <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> as
moderately or highly suspicious on the basis of medical records or cremation
documentation; and
• in the case of all the Todmorden deaths investigated by the police (save for the
one which fell outside the Inquiry’s Terms of Reference for Phase One).
2.33 The effect of applying these criteria was to leave unallocated, either to the ‘ closed’ or
‘ decision’ categories, a significant number of cases where no concern had been
expressed by relatives and which Professor <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> had assessed as non-suspicious or
had not been able to assess at all because of the absence of medical records or
cremation forms. These were mainly cases from the late 1970s and early 1980s and, in
many (152 at the time of the Opening Meeting of the Inquiry in May 2001), the only
information which the Inquiry had in its possession was a copy of the entry in the register
of deaths. The amount of information available in these cases increased as more
relatives were traced by means of enquiry agents and advertisements in the press, and
as additional documents – <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s visits books from the <LOCATION>Donneybrook</LOCATION> years, books
of MCCD counterfoils and daily report diaries from a residential care home, <ORGANIZATION>Charnley
House</ORGANIZATION> – came into the Inquiry’s possession, but the evidence still remained very limited
in some cases.
2.34 In the first instance, the legal team had intended that, of those cases with very little
available evidence, only those where there was some positive evidence that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>
had been, or might have been, involved in the death would be investigated and put
before me for decision; it was proposed that the remainder should be closed. As
mean that there would be few decisions and, moreover, no means by which the public
would be able to see the reasoning which had led to large numbers of cases being
28
The <ORGANIZATION>Shipman Inquiry</ORGANIZATION>
closed. There was also the risk that this approach would mean that some cases where
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> had killed would be missed.
2.35 It was decided, therefore, to change the approach. Instead of requiring positive
evidence of <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s involvement, the legal team would investigate as fully as
possible those cases where there was little information available and refer them to me
for decision, in the absence of compelling evidence that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> had not been
involved in the death.
2.36 From the first, the legal team had taken the view that the fact that family members had
no concerns about the death, or were positively opposed to the death being
investigated, would not prevent the Inquiry from investigating in a case where there was
real cause for suspicion. However, where there were no overtly suspicious
circumstances and the family, on being contacted, had declared that they had no
concerns about the death, it was initially thought appropriate to close the case.
2.37 Once the decision was taken to lower the threshold for determining which cases would
be placed before me for decision, it was recognised that the Inquiry’s stance in relation
to families expressing ‘ no concerns’ would also have to be changed. After all, the
relative of a deceased person may have ‘ no concerns’ about <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s involvement in
the death because he or she was with that person continuously during the days before
death and knows that <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> never visited; equally, he or she may have ‘ no concerns’
because, having being abroad at the time of the death, he or she knows nothing about
the circumstances of the death but has no positive reason to suspect <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s
involvement. In the first case, <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON> was obviously not implicated in the death; in the
second, it is impossible to know one way or another. In order to find out the true state of
affairs, it was necessary to approach families to ascertain precisely what they knew
about the circumstances of their relatives’ deaths. When this was done, it was
discovered that, in some cases where families had reported ‘ no concerns’, further
enquiries revealed that the circumstances of the death were such as to arouse
considerable suspicion about <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s possible involvement.
2.38 Naturally, the Inquiry has been reluctant to take any step which might disturb or upset
families who have, hitherto, had no worries about their relative’s death, or who had been
unwilling to voice any concerns which they may have had. It has, however, been
impossible to avoid approaching such families in some cases. I hope that those who
have been contacted by the Inquiry, in circumstances when they would have preferred
that this was not done, will understand that it was necessary in order to discharge the
Inquiry’s duty to obtain the fullest possible information about deaths occurring during
<PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s professional career. The vast majority of people from whom the Inquiry has
sought information have responded courteously and patiently and I am most grateful to
them for their co-operation.
29
CHAPTER THREE
The Evidence and the Oral Hearings
3.1 Having identified the cases to be investigated, the Inquiry team opened a file on each
death and the work of collecting and analysing the evidence began. Further staff were
taken on as necessary to assist with this work; the legal team reached maximum
strength at the end of the summer of 2001, by which time a further six solicitors – among
them Assistant Solicitors to the Inquiry, <PERSON>Mrs Julie Denham</PERSON> and Miss <PERSON>Julie Clarey</PERSON> – and a
total of nine paralegals had joined the legal team.
The Collection of the Evidence
3.2 The investigation of 888 cases has necessitated a huge evidence-gathering exercise on
the part of the Inquiry. A great deal of effort has gone into tracing witnesses, obtaining
documents and doing the type of ‘ detective work’ normally associated with police
investigations. The result of all this work has been the accumulation of an enormous
body of evidence, which I have drawn upon in order to reach my decisions. The main
sources of evidence upon which my decisions are based can be identified as follows.
Police Statements
3.3 The Inquiry has had access to 2311 witness statements which were taken by the police
in the course of their enquiries in <LOCATION>Todmorden</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Hyde</PERSON>.
Inquiry Witness Statements
3.4 In addition, the Inquiry has obtained a further 1378 statements from relatives and friends
of those persons whose deaths have been investigated, and from neighbours,
paramedics, district nurses, police officers, home helps, residential home and other
care staff – in short, anyone who might be able to shed some light on the circumstances
of any of the deaths under investigation. Generic statements were also obtained
from <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s practice staff, his former partners and others who had background
evidence which might assist in informing the Inquiry about the circumstances
surrounding the deaths.
3.5 Initially, the Inquiry employed solicitor agents, <LOCATION>Eversheds</LOCATION>, to take witness statements on
its behalf. That task was subsequently taken over by members of the Inquiry legal team.
The statements of those families who are legally represented were taken by their
solicitors, <PERSON>Alexander Harris</PERSON>, at the Inquiry’s request.
Coroner’s Documents
3.6 Where there was a post-mortem examination and/or an inquest at the time of the death,
the coroner’s files contained documents relating to the death; such documents also
sometimes existed if a case had been referred to the coroner but no post-mortem
examination followed. All the relevant files were obtained from the coroner as described
in Chapter Two.
30
The Shipman Inquiry
Documents Forming Part of the Death Registration and Cremation Certification Processes
3.7 The nature and significance of the documents created in the course of the death
registration and cremation certification processes are fully explained in Chapter Five.
Some of these documents, notably MCCDs and cremation Forms B, have been of great
importance in the decision-making process.
Practice Records
3.8 The Inquiry obtained from the police a full set of appointments sheets and surgery visits
books, together with other documents, from the Market Street Surgery; these have been
of the utmost importance in piecing together the events surrounding many of the deaths
being investigated. A visit to the Market Street Surgery by members of the Inquiry team
yielded further material.
3.9 Very few documents from the <LOCATION>Donneybrook</LOCATION> practice were available to the Inquiry until
October 2001, when <PERSON>Mrs Primrose Shipman</PERSON> delivered three boxes of documents which
had been cleared out of the Market Street Surgery in, she believes, about April 2001,
and stored at her home ever since. One of those boxes contained <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>’s visits
books from 1979 to 1992, which covered all but his very earliest time at <LOCATION>Donneybrook</LOCATION>.
Receipt of those books necessitated a complete reconsideration by the Inquiry of all
pre-1993 deaths in the light of the information which they contained.
3.10 The nature and purpose of the practice records is described further in Chapter Four.
Medical Records
3.11 Initially, the Inquiry obtained from the police 362 sets of general practitioner notes (also
known as ‘ <PERSON>Lloyd George</PERSON>’ notes) and hospital records. The Inquiry has since obtained a
substantial number of further medical records, as well as other records of a similar type,
such as district nursing notes.
3.12 Up to 1996, responsibility for the retention and destruction of general practitioner
records lay with the relevant <ORGANIZATION>Family Health Service Authority</ORGANIZATION> (FHSA); after that time,
responsibility devolved onto the local health authority. Until 1994, the rule was that the
records of deceased patients had to be retained by the <ORGANIZATION>FHSA</ORGANIZATION> for only three years after
the completion of all the administrative procedures connected with the death. Further
guidance was issued to authorities in July 1994. This guidance stipulated different
periods of retention for different categories of patient, the longest minimum period being
25 years. For ease, the local <ORGANIZATION>FHSA</ORGANIZATION> and, afterwards, the <ORGANIZATION>West Pennine Health Authority</ORGANIZATION>,
instituted a policy whereby all records would be kept for 25 years. Although theoretically
that should mean that all records from July 1991 onwards have been preserved, in
practice the new system took some time to implement and, consequently, few records
from 1991 survive. In general, therefore, records dating from before 1992 are not
available for examination.
3.13 From 1973, general practitioners were given the option of having the records of their
deceased patients returned to them at the expiration of the three year period. <PERSON>Shipman</PERSON>
was one of a number of Tameside general practitioners who availed himself of this
opportunity. He then stored them in a completely haphazard fashion in his house and
31
garage, where they were found by police who were searching the premises as part of
their investigation into <PERSON>Mrs Grundy</PERSON>’s death. Most of the records found there post-dated
1991, but there were some records relating to deaths occurring before that time. They
